[Music]
if you're looking for a machine learning
tutorial with python and jupyter
notebook
this tutorial is for you you're going to
learn how to solve a real world problem
using machine learning and python we're
going to start off with a brief
introduction to machine learning
then we're going to talk about the tools
you need and after that we're going to
jump straight into the problem we're
going to solve
you'll learn how to build a model that
can learn and predict the kind of music
people like
so by the end of this one hour tutorial
you will have a good understanding of
machine learning basics
and you'll be able to learn more
intermediate to advanced level concepts
you don't need any prior knowledge in
machine learning but you need to know
python fairly well
if you don't i've got a couple of
tutorials for you here on my channel the
links are below this video
i'm ashamed only and i'm super excited
to be your instructor on this channel i
have tons of programming tutorials that
you might find helpful
so be sure to subscribe as i upload new
tutorials every week
now let's jump in and get started
in this section you're going to learn
about machine learning which is a subset
of ai or
artificial intelligence it's one of the
trending topics in the world these days
and it's going to have a lot of
applications in the future
here's an example imagine i ask you to
write a program
to scan an image and tell if it's a cat
or a doc
if you want to build this program using
traditional programming techniques
your program is going to get overly
complex you will have to come up with
lots of rules to look for specific
curves
edges and colors in an image to tell if
it's a cat or a dog
but if i give you a black and white
photo your rules may not work
they may break then you'll have to
rewrite them or i might give you a
picture of a cat or a dog
from a different angle that you did not
predict before
so solving this problem using
traditional programming techniques is
going to get
overly complex or sometimes impossible
now to make the matter worse what if in
the future i ask you to extend this
program
such that it supports three kinds of
animals cats
dogs and horses once again you'll have
to rewrite all those rules
that's not gonna work so machine
learning is a technique to solve these
kind of problems
and this is how it works we build a
model or an engine
and give it lots and lots of data for
example we give you
thousands or tens of thousands of
pictures of cats and dogs
our model will then find and learn
patterns in the input data
so we can give it a new picture of a cat
that it hasn't seen before
and ask it is it a cat or a dog or a
horse and it will tell us with a certain
level of accuracy
the more input data we give it the more
accurate our model
is going to be so that was a very basic
example
but machine learning has other
applications in self-driving cars
robotics language processing vision
processing
forecasting things like stock market
trends and the weather
games and so on so that's the basic idea
about machine learning
next we'll look at machine learning in
action
a machine learning project involves a
number of steps the first step is to
import our data which often comes in the
form of a csv file
you might have a database with lots of
data we can simply export that data
and store it in a csv file for the
purpose of our machine learning project
so we import our data next we need to
clean it and this involves tasks
such as removing duplicated data if you
have duplicates in the data
we don't want to feed this to our model
because otherwise our model will learn
bad patterns in the data and it will
produce the wrong result
so we should make sure that our input
data is in a good and clean shape
if there are data that is irrelevant we
should remove them if they are
duplicated or
incomplete we can remove or modify them
if our data is text-based
like the name of countries or genres of
music
or cats and dogs we need to convert them
to numerical values
so this step really depends on the kind
of data we're working with
every project is different now that we
have a clean data set we need to split
it into
two segments one for training our model
and the other for testing it
to make sure that our model produces the
right result
for example if you have a thousand
pictures of cats and dogs
we can reserve eighty percent for
training and the other 20
for testing the next step is to create a
model
and this involves selecting an algorithm
to analyze the data
there are so many different machine
learning algorithms out there such as
decision trees
neural networks and so on each algorithm
has pros and cons
in terms of accuracy and performance so
the algorithm you choose
depends on the kind of problem you're
trying to solve and your input data
now the good news is that we don't have
to explicitly program an
algorithm there are libraries out there
that provide these algorithms
one of the most popular ones which we
are going to look at in this tutorial
is scikit-learn so we build a model
using an algorithm
next we need to train our model so we
fitted our training data
our model will then look for the
patterns in the data so next we can ask
it to make predictions
back to our example of cats and dogs we
can ask our model
is this a cat or a dog and our model
will make a prediction
now the prediction is not always
accurate in fact when you start out
it's very likely that your predictions
are inaccurate so we need to evaluate
the predictions and measure
their accuracy then we need to get back
to our model
and either select a different algorithm
that is going to produce
a more accurate result for the kind of
problem we're trying to solve
or fine-tune the parameters of our model
so each algorithm has parameters that we
can modify to optimize the accuracy
so these are the high level steps that
you follow in a machine learning project
next we'll look at the libraries and
tools for machine learning
in this lecture we're going to look at
the popular python libraries that we use
in machine learning projects
the first one is numpy which provides a
multi-dimensional array
very very popular library the second one
is pandas which is a data analysis
library that provides a concept called
data frame
a data frame is a two-dimensional data
structure similar to an excel
spreadsheet
so we have rows and columns we can
select data in a row or a column
or a range of rows and columns again
very very popular in machine learning
and data science projects the third
library
is matplotlib which is a two-dimensional
plotting library
for creating graphs and plots the next
library is scikit-learn which is one of
the most popular machine learning
libraries
that provides all these common
algorithms like decision trees
neural networks and so on now when
working with machine learning projects
we use an environment called jupiter for
writing our code
technically we can still use vs code or
any other code editors
but these editors are not ideal for
machine learning projects
because we frequently need to inspect
the data and that is really hard
in environments like vs code and
terminal if you're working with a table
of 10 or 20 columns
visualizing this data in a terminal
window is really really difficult and
messy
so that's why we use jupiter it makes it
really easy to inspect our data
now to install jupyter we're going to
use a platform called anaconda
so head over to anaconda.com
download on this page you can download
anaconda distribution for your operating
system
so we have distributions for windows mac
and linux so let's go ahead and
install anaconda for python 3.7
download
all right so here's anaconda downloaded
on my machine let's double click this
all right first it's going to run a
program to determine if the software can
be installed
so let's continue and once again
continue
continue pretty easy continue one more
time
i agree with the license agreement okay
you can use the default installation
location so don't worry about that
just click install give it a few seconds
now the beautiful thing about anaconda
is that it will install jupyter
as well as all those popular data
science libraries like numpy
pandas and so on so we don't have to
manually install this using pip
all right now as part of the next step
anaconda is suggesting to install
microsoft vs code we already have this
on our machine so
we don't have to install it we can go
with continue and
close the installation now finally we
can move this to trash because we don't
need this installer in the future
all right now open up a terminal window
and type
jupyter with a y space
notebook this will start the notebook
server on your machine
so enter there you go this will start
the notebook server on your machine you
can see these default messages here
don't worry about them now it
automatically opens a browser window
pointing to localhost port 888
this is what we call jupiter dashboard
on this dashboard we have a few tabs the
first tab
is the files tab and by default this
points to your home directory
so every user on your machine has a home
directory this is my home directory on
mac
you can see here we have a desktop
folder as well as documents
downloads and so on on your machine
you're going to see different folders
so someone on your machine you need to
create a jupyter notebook
i'm going to go to desktop here's my
desktop i don't have anything here
and then click new i want to create a
notebook
for python 3. in this notebook we can
write python code
and execute it line by line we can
easily visualize our data as you will
see over the next few videos
so let's go ahead with this
all right here's our first notebook you
can see by default it's called
untitled let's change that to hello
world
so this is going to be the hello world
of our machine learning project
let's rename this now if you look at
your desktop you can see this file
helloworld.i
pi nb this is a jupiter notebook
it's kind of similar to our pi files
where we write our python code
but it includes additional data that
jupiter uses to execute our code
so back to our notebook let's do a
print hello world and then
click this run button here and
here's the result printed in jupyter so
we don't have to navigate back and forth
between the terminal window
we can see all the result right here
next i'm going to show you how to load a
data set from a csv file in jupyter
all right in this lecture we're going to
download a data set from a very popular
website called
kaggle.com gaggle is basically a place
to do data science projects
so the first thing you need to do is to
create an account you can sign up with
facebook google or using a custom email
and password
once you sign up then come back here on
kaggle.com
here in the search bar search for
video game sales this is the name of a
very popular data set that we're going
to use in this lecture
so here in this list you can see the
first item
with this kind of reddish icon so let's
go with that
as you can see this data set includes
the sales data for more than 16
000 video games on this page you can see
the description
of various columns in this data set we
have rank
name platform year and so on so here's
our data source it's a csv file called
vgsales.csv
as you can see there are over 16 000
rows
and 11 columns in this data set right
below that you can see the first few
records
of this data set so here's our first
record the ranking for this game is one
it's the wii sports game for we as the
platform and it was released in year
now what i want you to do is to go ahead
and
download this data set and as i told you
before you need to sign in before you
can download this
so this will give you a zip file as you
can see here
here's our csv file now i want you to
put this
right next to your jupyter notebook on
my machine that is on my desktop
so i'm going to drag and drop this onto
the desktop folder
now if you look at the desktop you can
see here is my
jupyter hello world notebook and right
next to that we have
vgsales.csv with that
we go back to our jupyter notebook let's
remove the first line
and instead import
pandas as pd
with this we're importing pandas module
and renaming it to pd
so we don't have to type pandas dot
several times in this code
now let's type pd dot read
underline csv and pass the name of our
csv file
that is vg sales.csv now because this
csv file is in the current folder
right next to our jupyter notebook we
can easily load it otherwise we'll have
to supply the full path to this file
so this returns a data frame object
which is like an excel spreadsheet let
me show you so
we store it here and then we can simply
type
df to inspect it so one more time let's
run this program
here's our data frame with these rows
and columns so we have rank
name platform and so on now this data
frame object has lots of attributes and
methods
that we're not going to cover in this
tutorial that's really beyond the scope
of what we're going to do
so i'll leave it up to you to read
panda's documentation or follow other
tutorials to learn about pandas data
frames
but in this lecture i'm going to show
you some of the most useful methods
and attributes the first one is shape so
shape let's run this one more time so
here's the shape of this data set
we have over 16 000 records and
11 columns technically this is a two
dimensional array
of sixteen thousand and eleven okay
now you can see here we have another
segment for writing code so we don't
have to write all the code in the first
segment
so here in the second segment we can
call one of the methods of the data
frame
that is df dot describe
now when we run this program we can see
the output for each segment
right next to it so here's our first
segment here we have
these three lines and this is the output
of the last line below that we have our
second segment
here we're calling the describe method
and right below that we have
the output of this segment so this is
the beauty of jupiter
we can easily visualize our data doing
this with vs code and terminal windows
is really tedious and clunky
so what is this describe method
returning basically it's returning some
basic information about each column
in this data set so as you saw earlier
we have columns like rank
year and so on these are the columns
with numerical values
now for each column we have the count
which is the number of records in that
column
you can see our rank column has 16
598 records whereas the year column has
16 327 records
so this shows that some of our records
don't have the value for the year column
we have no values so in a real data
science or
machine learning project we'll have to
use some techniques to clean up our data
set
one option is to remove the records that
don't have a value for the year column
or we can assign them a default value
that really depends on the project
now another attribute for each column is
mean so this is the average
of all the values now in the case of the
rank column this value doesn't really
matter
but look at the year so the average year
for all these video games in our data
set
is 2006 and this might be important in
the problem we're trying to solve
we also have standard deviation which is
a measure
to quantify the amount of variation in
our set of values
below that we have min as an example the
minimum value for the year column
is 1980. so quite often when we work
with a new data set
we call the describe method to get some
basic statistics about our data
let me show you another useful attribute
so in the next segment let's type
df.values let's run this
as you can see this returns a
two-dimensional array this square
bracket indicates
the outer array and the second one
represents the inner array so the first
element
in our outer array is an array itself
these are the values in this array which
basically represent the first row
in our data set so the video game with
ranking 1
which is called wii sports so this was a
basic
overview of pando's data frames in the
next lecture i'm going to show you some
of the useful shortcuts of jupyter
in this lecture i'm going to show you
some of the most useful shortcuts in
jupyter
now the first thing i want you to pay
attention to is this green bar
on the left this indicates that this
cell is currently in the edit mode so
we can write code here now if we press
the escape key green turns to blue and
that means this cell is currently in the
command mode
so basically the activated cell can be
either in the edit mode or
the command mode depending on the mode
we have different shortcuts
so here we're currently in the command
mode if we press
h we can see the list of all the
keyboard
shortcuts right above this list you can
see
mac os modifier keys these are the extra
keys that we have on a mac keyboard
if you're a windows user you're not
going to see this so as an example here
is the shape of the command key this is
control this is
option and so on with this guideline you
can easily understand the shortcut
associated with each command
let me show you so here we have all the
commands
when a cell is in the command mode for
example we have this command
open the command palette this is exactly
like the command palette that we have in
vs code
here's a shortcut to execute this
command that is
command shift and f okay so here we have
lots of shortcuts of course you're not
going to use all of them all the time
but it's good to have a quick look here
to see what is available for you
with this shortcuts you can write code
much faster so let me show you some of
the most useful ones
i'm going to close this now with our
first cell
in the command mode i'm going to press b
and this inserts a new cell below this
cell
we can also go back to our first cell
press escape
now the cell is in the command mode we
can insert an empty cell
above this cell by pressing a
so either a or b a for above and b
for below okay now if you don't want
this cell you can press
d twice to delete it like this
now in the cell i'm going to print a
hello world message so
print hello world now
to run the code in this cell we can
click on the run button here
so here's our print function and right
below that you can see
the output of this function but note
that when you run a cell
this will only execute the code in that
cell
in other words the code in other cells
will not be executed let me show you
what i mean
so in the cell below this cell i'm going
to delete the call
to describe method instead i'm going to
print
ocean now i'm going to put the cursor
back in this cell where we print the
hello world message
and run this cell so you can see hello
world
is displayed here but the cell below is
still displaying
the described table so we don't see the
changes here
now to solve this problem we can go to
the cell menu on the top
and run all cells together
this can work for small projects but
sometimes you're working with a large
data set
so if you want to run all these cells
together it's going to take a lot of
time
that is the reason jupiter saves the
output of itself so we don't have to
rerun that code
if it hasn't changed so this notebook
file that we have here
includes our source code organized in
cells
as well as the output for each cell that
is why it's different
from a regular pi file where we only
have the source code
here we also have autocompletion and
intellisense
so in the cell let's call
df dataframe dot
now if you press tab we can see all the
attributes and methods
in this object so let's call
describe now with the cursor on the name
of the method we can press
shift and tab to see this tooltip that
describes
what this method does and what parameter
it takes so here in front of signature
you can see
the describe method these are the
parameters
and their default value and right below
that you can see
the description of what this method does
in this case it generates
descriptive statistics that summarize
the central tendency and so on
similar to vs code we can also convert a
line to comment
by pressing command and slash on mac or
control slash on windows
like this now this line is a comment we
can press the same shortcut
one more time to remove the comment
so these were some of the most useful
shortcuts in jupyter
now over the next few lectures we're
going to work on a real machine learning
project
but before we get there let's delete all
the cells here so we start with
only a single empty cell so here in this
cell
first i'm going to press the escape
button now the cell is blue
so we are in the command mode and we can
delete the cell by pressing d
twice there you go now the next cell
is activated and it's in the command
mode so let's delete this as well
we have two more cells to delete there
you go and the last one
like this so now we have an empty
notebook with a single cell
hey guys i just wanted to let you know
that i have an online coding school at
cordwindmarch.com where you can find
plenty of courses on web and mobile
development
in fact i have a comprehensive python
course that teaches you everything about
python from the basics to more advanced
concepts
so after you watch this tutorial if you
want to learn more you may want to look
at my python course it comes with a 30
day money back guarantee
and a certificate of completion you can
add to your resume in case you're
interested
the link is below this video
over the next few lectures we're going
to work on a real machine learning
project
imagine we have an online music store
when our users sign up we ask their age
and gender and based on their profile we
recommend
various music albums they're likely to
buy so in this project we want to use
machine learning to
increase sales so we want to build a
model
we feed this model with some sample data
based on the existing users
our model will learn the patterns in our
data so we can ask it to make
predictions
when a user signs up we tell our model
hey we have a new user with this profile
what is the kind of music that this user
is interested in
our model will say jazz or hip hop or
whatever
and based on that we can make
suggestions to the user so this is the
problem we're going to solve
now back to the list of steps in a
machine learning project
first we need to import our data then we
should prepare or clean it
next we select a machine learning
algorithm to build a model
we train our model and ask it to make
predictions
and finally we evaluate our algorithm to
see its accuracy
if it's not accurate we either fine tune
our model
or select a different algorithm so let's
focus on the first step
download the csv file below this video
this is a very basic csv that i've
created for this project
it's just some random made up data it's
not real
so we have a table with three columns
age gender
and genre gender can either be one which
represents a male
or zero which represents a female here
i'm making a few assumptions
i'm assuming that men between 20 and 25
like hip-hop
men between 26 and 30 like jazz
and after the age of 30 they like
classical music
for women i'm assuming that if they're
between 20 and 25 they like dance music
if they're between 26 and 30 they like
acoustic music
and just like men after the age of 30
they like classical music
once again this is a made-up pattern
it's not the representation of the
reality
so let's go ahead and download this csv
click on this
dot dot icon here and download this file
in my downloads folder here we have this
music.csv
i'm going to drag and drop this onto
desktop because that's where
i've stored this hello world notebook so
i want you to put the csv file
right next to your jupyter notebook
now back to our notebook we need to read
the csv file
so just like before first we need to
import the pandas module
so import pandas as pd
and then we'll call pd that read analyze
csv
and the name of our file is music.csv
as you saw earlier this returns a data
frame which is a two-dimensional array
similar to an excel spreadsheet so let's
call that
music underline data
now let's inspect this music underline
data to make sure we loaded everything
properly
so run so here's our data frame
beautiful next minute to prepare or
clean the data
and that's the topic for the next
lecture
the second step in a machine learning
project is cleaning or preparing the
data
and that involves tasks such as removing
duplicates
null values and so on now in this
particular data set we don't have to do
any kind of cleaning because we don't
have any duplicates
and as you can see all rows have values
for all columns so we don't have null
values but there is one thing we need to
do
we should split this data set into two
separate data sets
one with the first two columns which we
refer to as the input set
and the other with the last column which
we refer to as the output set
so when we train a model we give it two
separate data sets
the input set and the output set the
output set
which is in this case the genre column
contains
the predictions so we're telling our
model that if we have
a user who's 20 years old and is a male
they like
hip hop once we train our model then we
give it a new input set
for example we say hey we have a new
user who is 21 years old
and is a male what is the genre of the
music that this user probably likes
as you can see in our input set we don't
have a sample for a 21 year old male
so we're going to ask our model to
predict that
that is the reason we need to split this
data set into two separate sets
input and output so back to our code
this data frame object has a method
called drop
now if you put the cursor under method
name and press
shift and tab you can see this tooltip
so this is the signature of this drop
method these are the parameters that we
can pass here
the parameter we're going to use in this
lecture is columns which is set to none
by default
with this parameter we can specify the
columns we want to drop
so in this case we set columns
to an array with one string genre
now this method doesn't actually modify
the original data set
in fact it will create a new data set
but without
this column so by convention we use a
capital x
to represent that data set so capital x
equals this expression now
let's inspect x so as you can
see our input set or x includes these
two columns
age and gender it doesn't have the
output or predictions
next we need to create our output set so
once again we start with our data frame
music data
using square brackets we can get all the
values in a given column
in this case genre once again this
returns
a new data set by convention we use a
lowercase y
to represent that so that is our output
data set
let's inspect that as well
so in this data set we only have the
predictions or
the answers so we have prepared our data
next we need to create a model using an
algorithm
the next step is to build a model using
a machine learning algorithm
there are so many algorithms out there
and each algorithm has its pros and cons
in terms of the performance and accuracy
in this lecture we're going to use a
very simple algorithm called
decision tree now the good news is that
we don't have to explicitly
program these algorithms they're already
implemented for us in a library called
scikit-learn so here on the top
from sklearn.3
let's import the decision
tree classifier so sklearn
is the package that comes with
scikit-learn library this is the most
popular machine learning library in
python
in this package we have a module called
tree and in this module we have a class
called
decision tree classifier this class
implements
the decision tree algorithm okay so
now we need to create a new instance of
this class
so at the end let's create an object
called
model and set it to a new instance of
decision
tree classifier
like this so now we have a model next we
need to train it so it learns
patterns in the data and that is pretty
easy we call
model that fit this method takes two
data sets
the input set and the output set so
they are capital x and y
now finally we need to ask our model to
make a prediction
so we can ask it what is the kind of
music that a 21 year old male likes
now before we do that let's temporarily
inspect
our initial data set that is music data
so look what we got here
as i told you earlier i've assumed that
men between 20
and 25 like hip-hop music but here we
only have
three samples for men aged 20
23 and 25 we don't have a sample for a
21 year old male
so if you ask our model to predict the
kind of music that a 21 year old male
likes we expect it to say
hip hop similarly i've assumed that
women between 20 and 25
like dance music but we don't have a
sample for a 22 year old female
so once again if you ask our model to
predict the kind of music
that a 22 year old woman likes we expect
it to say
dance so with these assumptions
let's go ahead and ask our model to make
predictions
so let's remove
the last line and instead we're going to
call
model dot predict this method
takes a two dimensional array so here's
the outer array
in this array each element is an array
so i'm going to pass
another array here and in this array i'm
going to pass
a new input set a 21 year old male
so 21 comma one that is like a new
record
in this table okay so this is one input
set
let's pass another input set for a
22-year female
so here's another array here we add 22
comma zero so we're asking our model to
make two predictions at the same time
we get the result and store it in a
variable called predictions
and finally let's inspect that in our
notebook
run look what we got
our model is saying that a 21 year old
male
likes hip hop and a 22 year old female
likes
dance music so our model could
successfully make predictions here
beautiful but wait a second building a
model that makes predictions accurately
is not always that easy
as i told you earlier after we build a
model we need to measure its accuracy
and if it's not accurate enough we
should either fine tune it or build a
model using a different algorithm
so in the next lecture i'm going to show
you how to measure the accuracy of a
model
in this lecture i'm going to show you
how to measure the accuracy of your
models
now in order to do so first we need to
split our data set
into two sets one for training and the
other for testing
because right now we're passing the
entire data set
for training the model and we're using
two samples
for making predictions that is not
enough to calculate the accuracy of a
model
a general rule of thumb is to allocate
70 to 80 percent of our data
for training and the other twenty to
thirty percent for testing
then instead of passing only two samples
for making predictions
we can pass the data set we have for
testing we'll get the predictions
and then we can compare these
predictions with the actual values
in the test set based on that we can
calculate the accuracy
that's really easy all we have to do is
to import a couple of functions
and call them in this code let me show
you so first on the top
from sklearn the model
underline selection module we import
a function called train test split
with this function we can easily split
our data set into two sets
for training and testing now
right here after we define x and y sets
we call this function
so train test split
we give it three arguments x y
and a keyboard argument that specifies
the size of our test data set
so test underline size we set it to 0.2
so we are allocating 20 of our data for
testing
now this function returns a tuple so we
can unpack it into four variables
right here x underline train
x underline test y underline train
and y underline test
so the first two variables are the input
sets for training
and testing and the other are the output
sets
for training and testing now when
training our model
instead of passing the entire data set
we want to pass only
the training data set so x
underline train and y
underline train also when making
predictions
instead of passing these two samples we
pass x
underline test so that is the data set
that contains
input values for testing now we get
the predictions to calculate the
accuracy we simply have to compare these
predictions
with the actual values we have in our
output set
for testing that is very easy first on
the top we need to import
a function so from sklearn.metrics
metrics
import accuracy underlying score
now at the very end we call this
function so accuracy
score and
give it two arguments y underline test
which contains
the expected values and predictions
which contains the actual values now
this function returns
an accuracy score between zero to one so
we can store it here
and simply display it on the console
so let's go ahead and run this program
so the accuracy score is one or 100
percent
but if we run this one more time we're
going to see a different result
because every time we split our data set
into training and test sets
we'll have different data sets because
this function randomly picks data
for training and testing let me show you
so put the cursor
in the cell now you can see this cell is
activated note that if you click this
button here
it will run this cell and also inserts a
new cell
below this cell let me show you so if i
go to the second cell
press escape button now we are in the
command mode
press d twice okay now it's deleted
if we click the run button you can see
this code was executed and now we have a
new cell
so if you want to run our first cell
multiple times every time we have to
click this
and then run it and then click again and
run it it's a little bit tedious
so i'll show you a shortcut activate the
first cell
and press ctrl and enter
this runs the current cell without
adding a new cell
below it so back here let's run it
multiple times
okay now look the accuracy dropped to
0.75
it's still good so the accuracy score
here is somewhere between
75 to 100 but let me show you something
if i change the test size from 0.2
to 0.8 so essentially we're using only
of our data for training this model and
we're using the other 80
for testing now let's see what happens
when we run this cell multiple times
so control and enter look the accuracy
immediately dropped to 0.4
one more time now 46 percent
40 26 it's really really bad
the reason this is happening is because
we are using very little data
for training this model this is one of
the key concepts in machine learning
the more data we give to our model and
the cleaner the data is
we get the better result so if we have
duplicates
irrelevant data or incomplete values our
model will learn
bad patterns in our data that is why
it's really important to clean our data
before training our model now let's
change this back to 0.2
run this one more time okay now the
accuracy is one
75 percent now we drop to 50
again the reason this is happening is
because we don't have enough data
some machine learning problems require
thousands or even millions of samples
to train a model the more complex the
problem is the more data we need
for example here we're only dealing with
a table of three columns
but if you want to build a model to tell
if a picture is a cat or a dog or a
horse or a lion
we'll need millions of pictures the more
animals we want to support the more
pictures we need
in the next lecture we're going to talk
about model persistence
so this is a very basic implementation
of building and training a model to make
predictions
now to simplify things i have removed
all the code that we wrote in the last
lecture for
calculating the accuracy because in this
lecture we're going to focus
on a different topic so basically we
import our data set
create a model train it and then
ask it to make predictions now this
piece of code that you see
here is not what we want to run every
time we have a new user or every time we
want to make recommendations
to an existing user because training a
model can sometimes be really time
consuming
in this example we're dealing with a
very small data set that has
only 20 records but in real applications
we might have a data set
with thousands or millions of samples
training a model for that might take
seconds
minutes or even hours so that is why
model persistence is important
once in a while we build and train our
model and then we'll save it to a file
now next time we want to make
predictions we simply load the model
from the file and
ask it to make predictions that model is
already trained we don't need to retrain
it
it's like an intelligent person so let
me show you how to do this it's very
very easy
on the top from sklearn.externals
module we import
lib this job live object has methods for
saving
and loading models so after
we train our model we simply call
joblib dot dump
and give it two arguments our model and
the name of the file
in which we want to store this model
let's call that
music dash recommender
dot job lib that's all we have to do
now temporarily i'm going to comment out
this line we don't want to make any
predictions we just want to store our
trained model in a file
so let's run this cell with control and
slash
okay look in the output we have an array
that contains the name of our model file
so this is the return value of the dump
method
now back to our desktop right next to my
notebook you can see our job live file
this is where our model is stored it's
simply a binary file
now back to our jupyter notebook as i
told you before in a real application we
don't want to train a model
every time so let's comment out
these few lines so i've selected these
few lines on mac we can press
command and slash on windows control
slash
okay these lines are commented out now
this time instead of dumping our model
we're going to load it so we call the
load method we don't have the model we
simply pass
the name of our model file this returns
our trained
model now with these two lines we can
simply
make predictions so earlier we assumed
that men between 20 and 25
like hip-hop music let's print
predictions and see if our model is
behaving correctly or not
so control and enter there you go
so this is how we persist and load
models
earlier in this section i told you that
decision trees are the easiest to
understand and that's why we started
machine learning
with decision trees in this lecture
we're going to export our model in a
visual format
so you will see how this model makes
predictions
that is really really cool let me show
you so
once again i've simplified this code so
we simply import
our data set create input and output
sets
create a model and train it
that's all we are doing now i want you
to follow along with me
type everything exactly as i show you in
this lecture don't worry about
what everything means we're going to
come back to it shortly so
on the top from sklearn
import tree this object
has a method for exporting our decision
tree in a graphical format
so after we train our model let's call
tree dot export underline
graph vis now here are a few arguments
we need to pass
the first argument is our model the
second is the name of the output file
so here we're going to use keyword
arguments because this method takes so
many parameters and we want to
selectively pass
keyword arguments without worrying about
their order
so the parameter we're going to set is
out
underline file let's set this to
music dash recommender dot
d o t this is the dot format which is a
graph
description language you'll see that
shortly
the other parameter we want to set is
feature
underline names we set this to an array
of two strings age and
gender these are the features or the
columns
of our data set so they are the
properties or features of our data
okay the other parameter is class names
so class underline names we should set
this to the list of classes
or labels we have in our output data set
like hip hop jazz classical and so on
so this y data set includes all the
genres or all the classes of our data
but they're repeated a few times in this
data set so
here we call y dot unique this returns
the unique list of classes now we should
sort this alphabetically
so we call the sorted function and
pass the result a y dot unique
the next parameter is label we set this
to a string
all once again don't worry about the
details of these parameters we're going
to come back to this shortly
so set label to all then
round it to true and finally
filled to true so this is the end result
now let's run this cell using control
and enter
okay here we have a new file
music recommender dot dot that's a
little bit funny
so we want to open this file with vs
code so drag and drop this
into a vs code window
okay here's a dot format it's a textual
language for describing graphs
now to visualize this graph we need to
install an extension in vs code
so on the left side click the extensions
panel
and search for dot dot
look at the second extension here
graphviz or dot
language by staphon vs
go ahead and install this extension and
then reload vs code
once you do that you can visualize this
dot file
so let me close this tab all right
look at this dot dot here on the right
side click this
you should have a new menu open preview
to the site
so click that all right here's the
visualization
of our decision tree let's close the dot
file
there you go this is exactly how our
model makes predictions
so we have this binary tree which means
every node can have
a maximum of two children on top of each
node we have
a condition if this condition is true we
go to the child node on the left side
otherwise we go to the child node on the
right side so let's see what's happening
here
the first condition is age less than or
equal to 30.5
if this condition is false that means
that user is 30 years or older
so the genre of the music that they're
interested in is classical
so here we're classifying people based
on their profile
that is the reason we have the word
class here so a user who is 30 years or
older
belongs to the class of classical or
people who like
classical music now what if this
condition is true
that means that user is younger than 30.
so now we check the gender if it's less
than
0.5 which basically means if it equals
to 0
then we're dealing with a female so we
go to the child node here
now once again we have another condition
so we're dealing with a female who is
younger than 30.
once again we need to check their age so
is the age
less than 25.5 if that's the case then
that user likes dance music otherwise
they like acoustic music
so this is the decision tree that our
model uses to make
predictions now if you're wondering why
we have these floating point numbers
like 25.5 these are basically the rules
that our model generates
based on the patterns that it finds in
our data set
as we give our model more data these
rules will change so they're not always
the same
also the more columns or more features
we have our decision tree is going to
get more complex
currently we have only two features age
and gender
now back to our code let me quickly
explain the meaning of all these
parameters
we set fill to true so each box or each
node is filled with a color
we set rounded to true so they have
rounded corners
we set label to all so every node has
labels that we can read
we set class names to the unique list of
genres
and that's for displaying the class for
each node right here
and we set feature names to age and
gender
so we can see the rules in our notes
hey thank you for watching my tutorial i
hope you learned a lot and you're
excited to learn more
if you enjoyed this tutorial please like
and share it with others and be sure to
subscribe to my channel
as i upload new videos every week once
again thank you and i wish you all the
[Music]
best